Guide to the Lewis Hine Fellowship Photographs Collection, 2003-2008
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
- Maital Guttman Documentary Series, 2005-2006, (1 box)
  - DVD: Three in a Million: a Hero Book Story, 2005-2006 (Box 2)
    This film is a documentary that highlights three Hero Book stories from MADaboutART, an arts-based HIV education center in South Africa. A Hero Book is a hand made book in which the child is the author, illustrator, and main character. The aim of the One Child, One Hero Book campaign is for youth to share with other youth their own strategies in the face of problems. The documentary guides the viewer through the stories of three HIV positive individuals (two children and one young adult) who have created Hero Books. The prompts for the sharing of their stories include: 1. My Self-Portrait; 2. My Community's Problems and Strengths; 3. An Early Memory; 4. My Problem; 5. One Shining Moment - When I Overcame My Problem; 6. Tricks to Overcome My Problem; 7. Me, the Hero. The running time for this documentary is approximately twenty-five minutes.
- Kate Joyce Photographs Series, 2004-2005, (1 box)
  As a 2004-2005 academic year Lewis Hine Documentary Fellow, Joyce worked in South Africa with the nongovernmental organization Diketso Eseng Dipuo Community Development Trust (DEDI). This NGO focuses on empowering parents and facilitating early-childhood development programs in rural and informal settlements throughout South Africa's Free State province. Joyce was introduced to Grassland Phase II (the subject of her photograph series) through DEDI. Grassland Phase II is a government-subsidized settlement located on the fringe of an expanding black township in South Africa's judicial capital, Bloemfontein. This settlement was developed in an effort to address the land and housing needs of people living in the rapidly growing informal settlement of Bergman Square (a local municipality that was divided into 2,883 half-hectare [1.2 acre] sites in 2003 and renamed Grassland Phase II). Subsidized urban settlements, like Grassland Phase II, provide residents with a springboard for growth and independence from living environments that are no longer sustainable; however, this type of development is still characterized by urban sprawl and racial segregation. The title of Joyce's project is: Grassland Phase II: Residents and Government Reshaping South Africa's Informal Settlements.
  Thirty-three 10.5 x 16" black-and-white images and seven 10.5 x 16" color images on 13 x 19" paper. Captions taken from original texts. Includes DVD with collection photographs, documentary texts, and audio interviews.
  - Paper copy of full captions and introduction to body of work, 2004, (1 folder) (Box 3)
  - Black and White Prints Subseries, 2004
    All photographs are made in Grassland Phase II, Bloemfontein, South Africa by Kate Joyce.
    - Arm adjusting veil over girl's head (Box 3, Image 01)
      Preparation for a white wedding ceremony performed by Lesedi la Bophelo Cultural Group, a dance and drama group for children living in Grassland Phase II, Bloemfontein, South Africa, 2004.
    - Portrait of brother and sister with arms around each others shoulders (Box 3, Image 02)
      Siblings in front of their home, a four-room shack attached to a Black Apostolic church where their father is pastor. Grassland Phase II, Bloemfontein, South Africa, 2004.
    - Teapot and interior texture of wallpaper (Box 3, Image 03)
      Teapot against the texture of wallpaper made of newspaper advertisements. Grassland Phase II, Bloemfontein, South Africa, 2004.
    - Left-side, child in arms of a man, right-side, woman bending down lover large iron pots (Box 3, Image 04)
      Funeral ceremony feast. Grassland Phase II, Bloemfontein, South Africa, 2004.
    - Hand holding negative to light (Box 3, Image 05)
      Four years ago the owner of a tuck shop or dry goods store in Grassland Phase II fled his home of Bangladesh, leaving his wife and two children. Do you want to see them, he asks, pulling a negative of his children out of his wallet and holding it up to the light. Grassland Phase II, Bloemfontein, South Africa, 2004.
    - Two girls dancing in dust mote (Box 3, Image 06)
      Rehearsal, Lesedi la Bophelo Cultural Group. Grassland Phase II, Bloemfontein, South Africa, 2004.
    - Two children in chaotic-looking yard, foreground, large teapot steaming over fire (Box 3, Image 07)
      Children in front yard doing chores. Grassland Phase II, Bloemfontein, South Africa, 2004.
    - Looking into grave at casket while people crowd along its edge (Box 3, Image 08)
      Family and friends take turns throwing the first fistfuls of dirt into the deceased's grave. Grassland Phase II, Bloemfontein, South Africa, 2004.
    - Foreground, round plant bed, background, man squatting in rectangle garden plot (Box 3, Image 09)
      After Nicho's sister passed-away he moved into her shack. On his day off from work he plants his garden, both for food and decoration. Grassland Phase II, Bloemfontein, South Africa, 2004.
    - One tall pointed tree standing alone (Box 3, Image 10)
      A landscape formerly owned by Afrikaner farmers is reshaped as the land's new inhabitants fell trees and disassemble abandoned structures to harvest firewood and collect building materials. Grassland Phase II, Bloemfontein, South Africa, 2004.
    - Silhouette of large tree, below its branches a person tossing a little kid in the air (Box 3, Image 11)
      A young child finds playfulness in front of her home. Grassland Phase II, Bloemfontein, South Africa, 2004.
    - Portrait of woman standing in doorway looking at camera with hand to her chin (Box 3, Image 12)
      Ntabitseng requests a portrait in front of her home. Grassland Phase II, Bloemfontein, South Africa, 2004.
    - A map being held by three unidentifiable women (Box 3, Image 13)
      Women holding a map of Grassland Phase II showing the division of land into 2,883 individual half-hectare plots, referred to as sites. Grassland Phase II, Bloemfontein, South Africa, 2004.
    - Foreground, agave spines hanging over fence, background, minimalist shack (Box 3, Image 14)
      While several residents are busy upgrading their living structures with mud and cement brick, the majority of Grassland Phase II residents continue living in shacks. Grassland Phase II, Bloemfontein, South Africa, 2004.
    - Woman with house motif on shawl of her dress, service attendees in background (Box 3, Image 15)
      During a funeral service at the St. Johannes Lutheran Church for a deceased resident of Grassland Phase II. Grassland Phase II, Bloemfontein, South Africa, 2004.
    - Older woman reading newspaper under porch tarp (Box 3, Image 16)
      Elizabeth on her front porch a few weeks before her husband passes away. Grassland Phase II, Bloemfontein, South Africa, 2004.
    - Looking up the former driveway, wire fences down the middle, shacks surrounding (Box 3, Image 17)
      Flanked by lion statues, the former entry to an Afrikaner-owned farm is divided down the middle where two sites meet. Grassland Phase II, Bloemfontein, South Africa, 2004.
    - Foreground, white wall with lion statue on right, man in truck backing out of drive (Box 3, Image 18)
    - Left-side, inside shack is a girl with head on table, right-side, open door looking outside (Box 3, Image 19)
      An orphaned young girl lives with her grandmother, brother, two sisters, and nephew. Grassland Phase II, Bloemfontein, South Africa, 2004.
    - Woman holding dog surrounded by laughing children (Box 3, Image 20)
      Mpewane Adelineh Mananzi, matron of Lesedi la Bophelo (Light of Life) Creche, provides early childhood education for several children in Grassland Phase II. She recently opened her crèche and is receiving support and practical information from Diketso Eseng Dipuo Community Development Trust (DEDI) concerning the sustainability of her crèche. Grassland Phase II, Bloemfontein, South Africa, 2004.
    - Many children falling over themselves filling the frame (Box 3, Image 21)
      A group of children crowd around the camera's viewfinder, interrupting their chores. Grassland Phase II, Bloemfontein, South Africa, 2004.
    - Two sweaters hanging water marks on ground below (Box 3, Image 22)
      Wet laundry on the line. Grassland Phase II, Bloemfontein, South Africa, 2004.
    - Two children looking at each other divided by two long socks hanging on clothesline (Box 3, Image 23)
      Children handing out in the yard. Grassland Phase II, Bloemfontein, South Africa, 2004.
    - Left-upper corner, girl with head on bench looking at camera, cat crawling out from under bench below her, right-side, bottles and barrel (Box 3, Image 24)
      Child living with her grandparents, while her mother remains living in Lesotho. Her grandfather works at a golf course and her grandmother sells homemade African beer. Selling homemade beer is illegal, yet, because it is relatively inexpensive and easy to produce, many people find it to be a lucrative business, especially in the face of 40-45% unemployment rates among Grassland's population. Throughout the day neighbors come to drink at their house. Grassland Phase II, Bloemfontein, South Africa, 2004.
    - Dog in steeldrum doghouse (Box 3, Image 25)
      Fifty-gallon steel drum doghouse. Grassland Phase II, Bloemfontein, South Africa, 2004.
    - Left-side, unidentifiable kids picking bone, right-side, older man standing with cane (Box 3, Image 26)
      Shadrack's grandchildren pick the remaining pieces of meat from the bone after he has finished eating from it. Grassland Phase II, Bloemfontein, South Africa, 2004.
    - Boy in suit jacket carrying a plat of pap in one hand and mug with the word Dad on it in the other hand (Box 3, Image 27)
      At a community day celebration children are served soup and pap, a corn porridge, donated by the owner of a corner store. Grassland Phase II, Bloemfontein, South Africa, 2004.
    - On shack roof a wire toy car, man picking up pliers, kid on ladder with head resting in arms leaning against edge of roof (Box 3, Image 28)
      Repairing the roof. Grassland Phase II, Bloemfontein, South Africa, 2004.
    - Right side, man with dreadlocks in doorway, left-side, two zones painted on wall (Box 3, Image 29)
      Monaheng in the doorway of his home. Monaheng and his wife, Mpewane, moved into an abandoned farmhouse a year before the land it stood on was bought and died into the 2,883 individual half-hectare sites that now make up Grassland Phase II. Grassland Phase II, Bloemfontein, South Africa, 2004.
    - Girl with ice cream cone on dress and one end lifted by wind, looking at camera (Box 3, Image 30)
      During funeral preparations for her grandfather, four sheep are sacrificed the night of the vigil. Grassland Phase II, Bloemfontein, South Africa, 2004.
    - From above looking at a dusty horizon of shacks, foreground, a kid kicking a bottle (Box 3, Image 31)
      Nine-year old boy kicking a bottle dangling on a string in the wind and dust. He is visiting his mother during school vacation, but will return to his grandparent's home in a town several hundred kilometers away at the end of his two-week stay. His mother is unemployed and his father is in Johannesburg looking for work. Grassland Phase II, Bloemfontein, South Africa, 2004.
    - Man sitting in yard in chair facing camera, girl running in opposite direction, background, people walking along road (Box 3, Image 32)
      Dusk. Grassland Phase II, Bloemfontein, South Africa, 2004.
    - Hands smooth over fresh braids (Box 3, Image 33)
      Braiding her boyfriend's hair. Grassland Phase II, Bloemfontein, South Africa, 2004.
  - Color Prints Subseries, 2004
    - In front of shack, mother holding baby in air, girl in doorway, cement face of a woman hanging above door (Box 3, Image 34)
      Mother of seven, Elsie lifts her 3-week old son in front of the entrance of her home. Grassland Phase II, Bloemfontein, South Africa, 2004.
    - Inside shack with stove, shelving, and TV, door open looking outside (Box 3, Image 35)
      Despite a shack's outside appearance it is not uncommon to find modern appliances filling its interior spaces. In some homes these appliances are used, but for the majority they prove too expensive to actually plug in. Grassland Phase II, Bloemfontein, South Africa, 2004.
    - Dust motes and light daggers passing through burlap in otherwise dark room (Box 3, Image 36)
      Sun, dust and other elements of weather pass through holes in corrugated iron sheets and burlap that make-up this family's shack. Grassland Phase II, Bloemfontein, South Africa, 2004.
    - Portrait of pregnant woman in green dress inside shop (Box 3, Image 37)
      Margaret, 7 months pregnant, in her shop where she sells fruits and vegetables, snacks, paraffin, and other staple goods. Grassland Phase II, Bloemfontein, South Africa, 2004.
    - Kids embracing with hands waving above them, with sun spot halos (Box 3, Image 38)
      The embrace. Lesedi la Bophelo Cultural Group, a dance and drama group for children, perform a white wedding ceremony for the residents of Grassland Phase II. Grassland Phase II, Bloemfontein, South Africa, 2004.
    - Girl looking out window at camera (Box 3, Image 39)
      Dikeledi, 16, lives with her grandparents after being orphaned a year ago. Grassland Phase II, Bloemfontein, South Africa, 2004.
    - Shadow on floor (Box 3, Image 40)
      A child's shadow falls on a patchwork floor. Grassland Phase II, Bloemfontein, South Africa, 2004.
  - DVD: Site Insight: Mapping Grassland Phase II. Bloemfontein, South Africa, 2004-2005, (Still photo presentation of photographs from collection, as well as documentary text and interviews of individuals living with Grassland Phase II. Material concerning the situations and struggles the community encounters. 10-minute running time.) (Box 3)
    [Item has been removed and files mounted to server. Please contact a reference archivist for access to the files.]
- Elena Rue Photographs Series, 2005-2006, (1 box)
  As a 2005-2006 academic year Lewis Hine Fellow, Guttman worked with Hope for Children (HFC) in Addis Ababa, Ethiopia, beginning in January 2006. Hope for Children is a local, non-governmental organization that supports young children affected by HIV/AIDS by ensuring they have access to basic services, such as food, shelter, education, and medical care. HFC’s seven group homes are the size of a traditional Ethiopian family (six to eight children) and are headed by a group home mother. Once the children are brought together and given everything they need, HFC steps back to allow them to become a family. Rue spent time in each of Hope for Children’s group homes during her nine months in Ethiopia, and her photographs provide a sense of the family life within the group homes and give a face to the statistics within the media about HIV/AIDS orphans. All of the photographs were made by Rue in Ethiopia in 2006 for her project Love after Loss, and the names of the children have been changed to protect their identities.
  This collection includes twenty-one color photographs, one of which is a duplicate. There are seventeen 10.5 x 16" images, three 13 x 20" images, and one 15 x 15" image. Captions are taken from text of multimedia presentation.
  - Group home playroom (Box 4, Image 1)
  - Playing outside the group home (Box 4, Image 2)
  - Dreams of being a doctor (Box 4, Image 3)
    When I asked Tesfaye what he wants to be when he grows up, he answered that his dream is to be a doctor. The next day, a group of doctors came to the home to do check-ups, and Tesfaye received his first medical lesson.
  - Dreams of finding a cure (Box 4, Image 4)
    Salam slips off into a daydream as she comforts the group home mother who is HIV positive and feeling sick. Salam aspires to be a doctor when she grows up so she can cure her beloved group home mother.
  - Getting ready for school (Box 4, Image 5)
    After washing her face, Addis patiently waits for her group home mother to fix her hair for school.
  - In the neighbors' house, (2 prints, 10.5x16", and 13x20") (Box 4, Image 6)
    Alem and Mesfin (seated) are surrounded by the neighbors who took care of them. I accompanied Yewoinshet when she went to get the children to take them into HFC. I could see that the neighbors loved them dearly but could not be their caretakers.
  - Mother to all (Box 4, Image 7)
    In addition to running Hope for Children (HFC), founder and director Yewoinshet Masresha serves as a parental figure and confidant for many of the children.
  - Family (Box 4, Image 8)
    When at all possible HFC allows children to stay in their own communities and families. Sarah's aunt, and primary caretaker, points to a photograph of Sarah's mother who passed away from the virus several years ago.
  - Identification card (Box 4, Image 9)
    Alem shows off her mother's identification card, one of the only items she brought with her to the group home.
  - A moment alone outside the group home (Box 4, Image 10)
  - Comforting mother (Box 4, Image 11)
    Margaret, a group home mother, explains to me her sorrow at the departure of two of the children. Although the children's needs were met, they were unhappy in a controlled environment and decided to return to the streets of Addis Ababa.
  - Religion (Box 4, Image 12)
    Muslim and Christian children living together in the group homes has not caused a problem other than the different cooking requirements. When asked if they would rather live in separate homes, the children responded, We don't want to be separated, we are brothers and sisters. At present, living together seems to create understanding and tolerance, but I sensed that HFC staff members worried about what will happen when the children enter their teenage years.
  - In the group home (Box 4, Image 13)
  - Inseparable since week one (Box 4, Image 14)
    Rahel and Kaleb have been raised by Nazanet since they were both a few weeks old. They are inseparable and have a very special love for each other. Over the years the relationship between these two children has become an inspiration for people in the HFC community. When someone is having a bad day, the remedy is to go and visit Rahel and Kaleb.
  - Portrait with a flower (Box 4, Image 15)
    During an impromptu photo session, Abebech asked me to take her picture and struck a pose for the camera.
  - In the group home (Box 4, Image 16)
  - Mary's first week (Box 4, Image 17)
    Days after joining her new family Mary has begun to interact with the other children but is not yet ready to join them in the daily routines.
  - Sarah's injury (Box 4, Image 18)
    While playing outside her house Sarah suffered a terrible fall. The subsequent gangrenous infection took such a hold that she had to have her arm amputated. Hope For Children is currently raising money for a prosthetic arm. Medical attention for amputees in Ethiopia is limited, and many of them end up using their disability to beg on the street.
  - A missing generation (Box 4, Image 19)
    After their parents passed away Tesfaye and his older brother lived with their blind grandmother. Although the grandmother is no longer able to look after the two boys she visits them regularly. During this visit Tesfaye's grandmother touched his shoes, clothes, and face to make sure he was being well looked after. With my basic Amharic I was able to understand that she was whispering to him to study hard, mind his group home mother, and become an important person.
  - Aster comforts Eyerus (Box 4, Image 20)
    Each HFC group home is different, but the love and support the children give each other exists in every one of them. I was amazed to observe the empathy and understanding between children who were not born siblings but have become family.
- Amanda van Scoyoc Photographs Series, 2007-2008, (1 box)
  As a Lewis Hine Documentary Fellow, van Scoyoc spent the 2007-2008 academic year working with the nonprofit organization Roca, which means "rock" in Spanish. Located in Chelsea, a primarily immigrant, low-income neighborhood in Boston, Roca serves Greater Boston communities by helping at-risk youth become self-sufficient, responsible citizens. During her fellowship project, van Scoyoc worked closely with a group of six teenage mothers from a Roca parenting group to design a documentary project that would give them and 24 other young mothers from Roca an opportunity to tell their stories. She found that many these women focused their lives around the well-being of their children and, being familiar with the cycle of poverty, actively sought out opportunities to secure a better future for them. In order to document their stories, van Scoyoc made a formal portrait in each mother's home and conducted a detailed interview; then, each mother took her own photographs; and finally, van Scoyoc and the young women chose the images and mothers' own words that made up this exhibit. The title for van Scoyoc's project is: Raising Them Right: Young Motherhood in Chelsea, Massachusetts.
  Twenty-four 14 x 14" color images on 16 x 21" paper. All photos were made by Amanda van Scoyoc in Boston, Massachusetts, in 2007 and 2008. Photos were taken with a Hasselblad, scanned and printed with an Epson color printer. Captions taken from original texts.
  - Paper copy of introduction and captions, 2008, (1 folder) (Box 5)
  - DVD: Amanda van Scoyoc, Hine Fellow 2007-2008, (jpeg files of final show, captions, introduction) (Box 5)
    [Item has been removed and files mounted on server. Please contact a reference archivist regarding access to files.]
  - I told my mom. She said she knew already because of her dream. Where we're from in Jamaica, when you have a dream about fishes that means that somebody in your family is having a baby. I'm my mother's only child, so she knew I was having a baby. Christina (17) and Mariyah (1 month). (Box 5, Image 01)
  - Before I had him, I didn't want to hold him immediately after he was born because I thought he would be so nasty and disgusting. But when he came out, I wanted to hold him. I cried. I told the doctor, "I can keep him, I can keep him." You know, I don't need to return him or anything. Christina (20), her boyfriend, and Isaih (1). (Box 5, Image 02)
  - I had missed my period a lot of times, and I didn't go to the doctors to get myself checked. So when I was about five and a half months pregnant, I finally went in. I asked my doctor if I could get a pregnancy test, and she just laughed at me and said that I don't need a pregnancy test. She went and got the prenatal lady and got the machine so you can hear the baby's heart beat. Desiree (23) and Marcus (4). (Box 5, Image 03)
  - When I was young, I used to say, "I don't want to have a kid because I don't want them to grow up, I want them to stay a baby." But then seeing him learn how to walk, learn how to crawl, everything; like it's amazing. Erica (22) and James (4). (Box 5, Image 04)
  - The main reason we are still together is Denise. I grew up without my father and I don't want her to go through that. We have our problems and stuff, but we put them aside and deal with them so that Denise can have both parents under the same roof. Inalvis (24) and Denise (6). (Box 5, Image 05)
  - My mom had her first child at 18. My sister had her first child at 18. And me, I'm the one in the family that broke it. It's almost like once you hit 18 you're an adult and they look at you weird if you don't have a kid already. Jackie (26), Elijah (1), and her mom. (Box 5, Image 06)